<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="execution.methods.for.phpspec">
  <title>Execution Methods for PHPSpec</title>

  <para>PHPSpec offers two distinct modes for executing specs or examples. The
  method most used throughout this manual requires using the command line
  <classname>phpspec</classname> operation from a console like bash or MS-DOS.
  An alternative method is available for executing specs by opening a .php URL
  in your preferred web browser. This alternative can output in either plain
  text or HTML as determined by various options.</para>

  <section id="the.console.runner">
    <title>The Console Runner</title>

    <para>Using PHPSpec from the console is the default option which requires
    no additional work from your perspective. Simple write your specs,
    navigate to their location on the command line, and issue a command
    like:</para>

    <screen>phpspec --recursive</screen>

    <para>This simple command recursively scans the current directory, and all
    child directories, for spec files and executes all the examples each spec
    file contains. The simplicity of this method makes using the console the
    most obvious choice. If you're using a Unix console then you even get some
    coloured output!</para>

    <para>The <classname>phpspec</classname> console command has a number of
    useful options which will be expanded substantially as development of
    subsequent versions progresses. Each option usually has both a full length
    version, and a shorter single character version. A table of the currently
    available options is presented below.</para>

    <table>
      <title>PHPSpec Console Options</title>

      <tgroup cols="3">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Fulltext Variant</entry>

            <entry align="center">Single Character Variant</entry>

            <entry align="center">Explanation</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>--recursive</entry>

            <entry>-r</entry>

            <entry>Recursively search the current directory and all child
            directories for specs, and execute all spec files and their
            examples as found.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>--reporter=[html/console/text]</entry>

            <entry><emphasis>None</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Use one of the available reporters to format output as
            either HTML, Text, or standard Console output. The default depends
            on the scenario but always defaults to Console when PHPSpec is run
            from the command line.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>--specdoc</entry>

            <entry>-s</entry>

            <entry>Add specdoc output (i.e. a plain text list of all
            specifications) to the results output for all reporters.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section id="the.http.runner">
    <title>The HTTP Runner</title>

    <para>The HTTP Runner is not an immediately available mode. Instead you
    need to do a small amount of setup within a PHP file which you intend
    calling from a web browser. This is actually a really simple task, and the
    available options for utilising a HTTP runner are identical to the options
    available for the Console Runner as outlined above.</para>

    <para>Here's a simple example of a HTTP Runner stored to a file called
    AllSpecs.php.</para>

    <programlisting role="php">&lt;?php

require_once 'PHPSpec.php';

$options = new stdClass;
$options-&gt;recursive = true;
$options-&gt;specdocs = true;
$options-&gt;reporter = 'html';

\PHPSpec\Runner::run($options);</programlisting>

    <para>The <classname>\PHPSpec\Runner</classname> class is actually used
    internally by the default Console Runner so what we're doing here is
    pretty simple. All we're really doing is duplicating the internal work the
    Console Runner performs within a PHP file we can visit from a web
    browser.</para>

    <para>First of all, we include the base PHPSpec.php file. Since PHPSpec
    takes advantage of PHP5 autoloading, there's no need to include any other
    PHPSpec files. Secondly, we setup the desired options in a
    <classname>stdClass</classname> (a PHP5 standard class) as object
    properties - optionally you can also use a plain array since it will just
    be converted to a standard object internally anyway.</para>

    <para>The options are typical for a complete execution of all specs.
    PHPSpec will recursively search the current directory and all child
    directories for specs to execute, it will output specdoc formatted
    specifications in plain text along with the results, and it will use the
    HTML reporter to output HTML.</para>

    <para>Finally we call PHPSpec_Runner's static run() method. And that's all
    there is to it! If you only want to execute a sub-directory of your specs,
    you can copy a similar file to that directory (recursive searching does
    not traverse parent directories).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>