<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="installation">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <para>PHPSpec should be installed using the PEAR Installer. PEAR (PHP
  Extension and Application Respository) is a simple, easy to use mechanism
  for distributing and managing PEAR packages. If you have PHP installed,
  chances are you already have a PEAR system ready to be utilised.</para>

  <section id="installing.phpspec.with.pear">
    <title>Installing PHPSpec with PEAR</title>

    <para>PHPSpec is distributed primarily from its own dedicated PEAR
    channel. The PEAR Channel system is quite simple to use and eases the
    installation of PHPSpec in any scenario where you have access to your own
    PEAR installation. Before commencing an installation, you first need to
    "discover" the PHPSpec channel using the command:</para>

    <screen>pear channel-discover pear.phpspec.org</screen>

    <para>The newly discovered channel will have its details stored by
    PEAR.</para>

    <para>Installing is dependent on the version, and preferred release state.
    At the time of writing PHPSpec is released as beta so you would use a
    command of the form:</para>

    <screen>pear install phpspec/PHPSpec-beta</screen>

    <note>
      <para>If PHPSpec has any stable release, the suffix "-beta" is not
      required.</para>
    </note>

    <note>
      <para>Development snapshots of PHPSpec are regularly updated at <ulink
      url="http://dev.phpspec.org">http://dev.phpspec.org</ulink>. These
      snapshots are considered of dubious stability and should only be
      utilised for testing and feedback purposes. The installation of
      development snapshots is described in the "Installing PHPSpec Manually"
      section below.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing PHPSpec from a PEAR download</title>

    <para>To install PHPSpec without using the PEAR channel system you can
    select a download of the PEAR archive from <ulink
    url="http://pear.phpspec.org/get">http://pear.phpspec.org/get</ulink> and
    by running the following command:</para>

    <screen>pear install -f PHPSpec-0.2.0devel.tgz</screen>

    <para>PEAR will do all the hard work, including installing the
    <classname>phpspec</classname> command line script. In the future we will
    publish public releases using a dedicated PEAR channel. This installation
    option is not much different than installing normally through PEAR. If you
    require a fully manual installation process - the next section will
    help.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installing.phpspec.manually">
    <title>Installing PHPSpec Manually</title>

    <para>To install PHPSpec manually, you can use the non-Pearified tarball
    called "PHPSpec-0.2.0beta.tar.gz" available for download from <ulink
    url="http://pear.phpspec.org/get/nonpear">http://pear.phpspec.org/get/nonpear</ulink>.
    Extract to your preferred location, and add the "src" directory to your
    php.ini include_path. You will also need to copy the phpspec script for
    your system (*.bat refers to a Windows friendly version) from the
    "scripts" directory to a location on your system PATH. This script must be
    edited to provide the location of the PHP binary executable as well as the
    path to the \PHPSpec\Console\Command classfile.</para>
  </section>
</section>